Nick Karanovich Collection of James B. Pond’s Photographs and Journal from Mark Twain’s North American Lecture Tour of 1895
Elmira College
Nick Karanovich Collection of James B. Pond’s Photographs and Journal from Mark Twain’s North American Lecture Tour of 1895
1984 - 1985
The collection contains 130 photographs reproduced from the original nitrate negatives of James B. Pond’s photographs of Mark Twain on his North American Lecture Tour, accompanied by his wife and daughter, Olivia Langdon Clemens and Clara Clemens as well as by Major Pond’s wife, Marion Glass Pond. The collection includes a copy of James B. Pond’s typescript draft of his account of Mark Twain in “Eccentricities of Genius” and a typescript copy of his journal from the tour.
1.17 Linear ft. (5 boxes)
Karanovich, Nicholas
Mark Twain Archive, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, N.Y.
unrestricted.
The bankruptcy of the Charles L. Webster Company in 1894 and the failure of the outperformed Paige Compositor typesetting machine, Mark Twain’s principle business ventures, placed Twain in an difficult financial position. Twain under pressures from creditor’s and family responsibilities conceived of a global lecture tour to settle his debts.
James B. Pond, a successful lecture manager was hired for the North American leg of the tour. Pond’s photographs and private journal are largely responsible for documenting the North American leg of the tour that went largely undocumented in Following the Equator, Mark Twain’s travelogue of the experience.
The photographs and journals follow the entourage from Cleveland, Ohio, July 15th to Vancouver, British Columbia, August 23, 1895. Major Pond, Martha and son, Bim, visit Quarry Farm on the return trip, where photographs of Susan Crane, Charles Langdon, Susy Clemens and Jean Clemens are captured on September 15, 1895
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Clemens, Olivia Langdon, 1845-1904; Clemens, Clara; Pond, James B. (James Burton), 1838-1903; Pond, Martha Marion Glass; Facsimiles; Photographs
The bulk of this collection has been published in Overland with Mark Twain: James B. Pond’s Photographs and Journal of the North American Lecture Tour of 1895, published by the Center of Mark Twain Studies in 1992 and containing 130 photographs reproduced from the original nitrate negatives of James B. Pond’s photographs of Mark Twain on his North American Lecture Tour, accompanied by his wife and daughter, Olivia Langdon Clemens and Clara Clemens as well as by Major Pond as the lecture manager, and his wife, Marion Glass Pond. The collection includes a copy of James B. Pond’s typescript draft of his account of Mark Twain used in “Eccentricities of Genius” and a typescript copy of his journal from the tour. Also included are notes, research materials and photocopied images containing additional information that were additional resources used in the publication of the Overland with Mark Twain.
- SERIES 1: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1984 - 1985; The series is constructed loosely by date. Not all dates and location are known and, therefore, there may be inconsistences. The order of these photographs follows the publication, Overland with Mark Twain: James B. Pond’s Photographs and Jouranl of the North American Lecture Tour of 1895. This series is organized and described at the item level.
  - Samuel L. Clemens and Major Pond, Mrs. Clemens, Clara Clemens, and Mrs. Pond aboard the S. S. Warimoo, August 23, 1895
  - Olivia Clemens, Samuel L. Clemens, and Mrs. Pond enroute to the S. S. Northland, Cleveland, July 17, July 17, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond and Clemens aboard the S. S. Northland, Cleveland, July 17, July 17, 1895
  - Clemens, Clara Clemens and Olivia aboard the S. S. Northland leaving Cleveland, July 18, July 18, 1895
  - Olivia urging Clemens to wear his overcoat. Aboard the S. S. Northland, July 18 (1), July 18, 1895
  - Olivia urging Clemens to wear his overcoat. Aboard the S. S. Northland, July 18 (2, July 18, 1895
  - Clemens aboard the S. S. Northland at railing looking out to sea, July 18, July 18, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond (foreground) and Olivia (at left) aboard the S. S. Northland, July 18, July 18, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond aboard the T. S. Faxon, July 19, July 19, 1895
  - Officer holding young child aboard the T. S. Faxton July 19, July 19, 1895
  - Mackinaw Island from the T. S. Faxton, July 19, July 19, 1895
  - Arrival at Mackinaw Island from the T. S. Faxton. The Grand Hotel is in the distance, July 19, July 19, 1895
  - Clara and Clemens standing on platform with train to the left. Location uncertain, Probably July 24th or 25th, July 24 or 25, 1895
  - Olivia (at left) and Mrs. Pond aboard the train, July, July, 1895
  - View of the train tracks from the train, July, July, 1895
  - Clara and Mrs. Pond aboard the train, July Clara. Train Station, Gretna, Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - Unidentified individuals, Mrs. Pond, Clara. Roof of the Hotel Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - Clara petting dog. Train Station. Gretna, Manitoba, July 25, July 25, 1895
  - Olivia and Clemens on platform with train in background, Gretna, Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - The party waiting to pass customs, Gretna, Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - Major Pond (center) and Clara. (Clemens and Olivia visible over Clara's shoulder), Gretna, Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - Clemens (seated) and Olivia, Mrs. Pond and Clara (foreground), Gretna, Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - View of Winnipeg from the roof of the Hotel Manitoba, July 26 (1), July 26, 1895
  - View of Winnipeg from the roof of the Hotel Manitoba, July 26 (2), July 26, 1895
  - Clemens sitting on platform. Gretna, Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - Clara, Mrs. Pond, Major Pond. Roof of the Hotel Manitoba, Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 26, July 26, 1895
  - Clara with English host (foreground), Mrs. Pond and Olivia, Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, July 27, 1895
  - Clara, Mrs. Pond and Olivia with young English gentlemen, Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, July 27, 1895
  - Olivia and English gentleman (in carriage at left), Clara and Mrs. Pond with English gentlemen (in carriage at right), Buffalo enclosure. Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, July 27, 1895
  - Olivia and English gentleman (in carriage at left), Clara and Mrs. Pond with English gentlemen (in carriage at right), Buffalo enclosure. Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, July 27, 1895
  - Buffalo enclosure, Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, July 27, 1895
  - Clara and English gentleman. Buffalo Enclosure, Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, July 27, 1895
  - Clara, Mrs. Pond and Olivia sitting with Englishmen standing behind. Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, July 27, 1895
  - Clemens, Mrs. Pond and Major Pond standing next to a pair of horses and cart, Winnipeg, Manitoba, July 27, 1895
  - The Party and other travelers departing Winnipeg, standing on the train platfor with train behind, July 27, 1895
  - Major Pond holding cart with a seated Clemens, Mrs. Pond to the left and Olivia to the right. Waiting for the train. Five A. M., Crookston, Minnesota, July 30, July 30, 1895
  - Clemens, Mrs. Pond, Olivia and Clara standing on platform with train to the left. Grand Fork, North Dakota, July 30, July 30, 1895
  - Leaving Grand Fork, train trails with platform and station on the right. North Dakota, July 30, July 30, 1895
  - Clemens looking towards the horizon, Railroad Station, Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens looking towards camera, Railroad Station. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Great Falls bridge, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond standing by rail on the bridge. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond and Major Pond sitting in car on the bridge. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond and Clara looking toward the dam. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clara, Clemens, Mrs. Pond, Gibson and Olivia. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond and Clara looking down towards dam and town in the distance. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - "Giant Springs," Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clara. "Giant Springs," Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Major and Mrs. Pond with bridge in the background. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Gibson, Clara, Olivia, Clemens and Mrs. Pond on dock. "Giant Springs," Great Flalls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens talking to family. Norewegian Shanty Town. Great Flals, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Two women in front of shanty. Norwegian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Cat. Norwegian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens sitting talking to gentleman in front of small shanty. Norwegian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens walking towards little girl. Norweigian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - The little girl hesistates. Norwegian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens with kittens and the little girl's family. Norwegian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens sitting with the little girl's family standing nearby. Norwegian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens leaving the little girl and her family. Norwegian Shanty Town. Great Falls, Montana, July 31, July 31, 1895
  - Clemens and D. C. K. Cole. Lobby of the Helena Hotel. Helena, Montana, August 4, August 4, 1895
  - Clemens and Senator Sanders. Missoula, Montana, August 5, August 5, 1895
  - Mrs. Henry Ward Beecher, Senator Sanders and Clemens. Missoula, Montana, August 5, August 5, 1895
  - Mrs. Henry Ward Beecher and Senator Sanders. Missoula, Montana, August 5, August 5, 1895
  - Mrs. Henry Ward Beecher and unidentified individuals. Missoula, Montana, August 5, August 5, 1895
  - Major Pond, Clara, Clemens and Olivia standing in street with horse and cart and buildings behind. Probably Missoula, Montana, August 5, 1895
  - Man on a bicycle leading a horse to the blacksmiths shops. "The decadence of the horse." Missoula, Montana, August 5, August 5, 1895
  - Clemens talking with soldiers on sidewalk. Fort Missoula, Montana, August 6, August 6, 1895
  - Clemens sitting with officer with another man standing behind Clemens. Fort Missoula, Montana, August 6, August 6, 1895
  - Clemens and Colonel Burt. Fort Missoula, Montana, August 6, August 6, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, Clara, Olivia, Clemens and Colonel Burt. Fort Missoula, Montana, August 6, 1895
  - Montana, possibly August 2?, August 2, 1895
  - Montana, possibly August 2?, August 2, 1895
  - Clara sitting in field with a house in the background to the right [undated]
  - Mrs. Pond, Olivia, Clara in field with house in background[undated]
  - Olivia, Major Pond, Mrs. Pond in field with two homes in background[undated]
  - I.O.O. F. Hall, location unknown, undated
  - Clara standing behind a seated Clemens [location unknown], undated
  - Clemens smoking a cigar [location unknown], undated
  - Clemens aboard the engine. The Great Northern, August 8/9, August 9, 1895
  - Major Pond aboard the engine. The Great Northern, August 8/9, August 9, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, Clara, Clemens and Major Pond. Crossing the Rockies. The Great Northern, August 9, August 9, 1895
  - Clemens aboard the steamer Flyer. Seattle, August 8, August 8, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, Clara and Olivia standing next to a taxidermied buffalo. Tacoma Hotel. Tacoma, Washington, undated
  - Clemens and reporters. Columbia River Ferry. Portland, Oregon, August 9, August 9, 1895
  - Clemens and reporters. Columbia River Ferry. Portland, Oregon, August 9, August 9, 1895
  - Reporters, Clemens and Major Pond. Columbia River Ferry. Portland, Oregon, August 9, August 9, 1895
  - Reporter and Clemens. Columbia River Ferry. Portland, Oregon, August 9, August 9, 1895
  - Lute Pease of the Portland Oregonian and Clemens. Portland, Oregon, August 9, August 9, 1895
  - Clemens in Hotel room. Olympia, Washington, August 11, August 11, 1895
  - Clara, Mrs. Pond, Olivia and Samuel Moffett aboard the steamer Flyer. Tacoma, Washington, August 13, August 13, 1895
  - Samuel Moffett, Olivia, Clara, Clemens, unidentified guest, Mrs. Pond and Officer aboard the U. S. S. Mohican, August 13, August 13, 1895
  - Clara, Clemens, Samuel Moffett and Olivia aobard the steamer Flyer. Tacoma, Washington, August 13, August 13, 1895
  - Clemens aboard the U. S. S. Mohican. Seattle, Washington, August 13, August 13, 1895
  - Samuel Moffett, Olivia, Clara Clemens, unidentified guest, Mrs. Pond and officers aboard the U. S. S. mohican, August 13, August 13, 1895
  - Samuel Moffett, Olivia, Major Pond, Clara, Clemens and Mrs. Pond aboard the U. S. S. Mohican, August 13, August 13, 1895
  - Clemens in bed talking with reporters. Hotel Vancouver, British Columbia, August 17, August 17, 1895
  - S. S. Warimoo. Vicotira, British Columbia, August 23, August 23, 1895
  - Clara, Olivia and Mrs. Pond on deck behind a "Notice" sign. The S. S. Warimoo. Victoria, British Columbia, August 23, August 23, 1895
  - Major Pond, Clemens, Clara and Olivia aboard the S. S. Warimoo. Victoria, British Columbia, August 23, August 23, 1895
  - Clemens, Clara, and Olivia aboard the S. S. Warimoo behind a "Notice" sign. Victoria, British Columbia, August 23, August 23, 1895
  - Clemens Aboard the S. S. Warimoo smoking a pipe. Victoria, British Columbia, August 23, August 23, 1895
  - S. S. Warimoo sailing for Australia, August 23, August 23, 1895
  - Unidentified individual, Susy Clemens and Susan Crane on Porch with Major Pond, Mrs. Pond and Bim seated in carriage. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Susan Crane, Mrs. Pond, Bim, Susy, and the dogs, Osmon and Bruce seated on porch. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York. September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Susan Crane, Mrs. C. J. Langdon, Major Pond, Bim, Susy, C. J. Langdon and Mrs. Pond on porch. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Bim, Susan Crane, Osmon and Susy on porch. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York. September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Unidentified individual, Jean Clemens, unidentified individual, Bim, unidentified individual, Bruce, Osmon and Susan Crane in front of porch. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, C. J. Langdon, unidentified individual, Susan Crane and unidentified individual seated in parlor reading a note from the Clemens'. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Unidentified individual, Jean, unidentified individual, Bim, unidentified individual, Osmon in front of porch. Quarry Farm, Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, C. J. Langdon, unidentified individual, Susan Crane seated in parlor. Quarry Farm, Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, Bim and Major Pond in Dining Room. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Susan Crane, Bim, Susy and Mrs. Pond at table in dining room. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York. September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Susy, servant, Susan Crane, Bim and Mrs. Pond at table in dining room. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Bim and Osmon outside in front of tree. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Bim, Susan Crane, Osmon and Bruce, Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Susan Crane, Bim and Osmon. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Jean (on the roof), Bim, Osmon, Bruce and Susan Crane. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Bim outside and Susan Crane and Osmon inside at the open window. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Bim with dog. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Osmon, unidentified individual. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Bim outside on a path with buildings behind. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Susan Crane with umbrella, Osmon, Bim and Mrs. Pond walking. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - The view from Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, Bim, Susan Crane and Osmon with landscape of East Hill behind. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York. September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Bim, Susy, Osmon, Susan Crane and Mrs. Pond. The Tent. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Susan Crane, Bim and Mrs. Pond. The Tent. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 18, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond, Julia Beecher holding two cats and Bim. The Beecher home. East Hill. Elmira, New York, September 16, September 16, 1895
  - Bim standing next to a tree and fence. Quarry Farm. Elmira, New York, September 15, September 15, 1895
  - Mrs. Pond sitting at table [location unknown], undated
  - Major Pond sitting at table [location unknown], undated
- SERIES 2: JOURNAL ENTRIES AND RESEARCH MATERIALS, undated; This series is comprised of facsimiles. This series is arranged alphabetically by folder title. This series is arranged at the folder level.
  - James Pond Journal -- edited typescripts of journal entries and excerpt on Mark Twain published in Pond's, Eccentricities of Genius[copies] [undated]
  - Research Notes and Materials -- Contains notes on chronological organization of photographs, reproduced excerpts from Eccentricities of Genius and Susy and Mark Twain: Family Dialogues, photocopied photos with notes [undated]
  - Set of photographs -- photocopied, with notes on origination [undated